Schlesinger, Emil. Collection 6036/018
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Schlesinger, Emil. Collection
1947-1968
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Schlesinger, Emil
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
6036/018
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection includes letters, briefs, cases and investigations of the garment industry as it relates to Emil Schlesinger and his legal counsel for the union.
5767592
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 06, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 22, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Emil Schlesinger was born on December 27, 1900, the son of Benjamin and Rachel Schlesinger. Schlesinger graduated from City College in June 1921 and began Columbia Law School in September 1921, graduating in 1924. He worked for Morris Hilquit from 1922-1925 while he was a law student and after graduation until he was able to open his own law office and practice in January 3, 1926, though he continued to do trial work and argue cases in court for Hillquit. In 1929 he became the general counsel for the Cloakmakers union and in 1933 represented the Joint Board of the Dressmakers union. Schlesinger provided legal counsel to the ILGWU and represented various locals of the union including Local 10 and Local 102. He died January 5, 1992.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection contains material that is of a legal and legislative nature, as Emil Schlesinger provided counsel for the ILGWU and Cutter's Local 10. The correspondence, reports, transcripts, and amendments to pending legislation mainly involve the cases and matters that Schlesinger and his law offices had some involvement. Some of the information contained in the collection includes radio speeches regarding legislation, reports on health and welfare fund restrictions, and briefs of labor relations, wages, and collective bargaining. There are files on restrictive labor bills, along with reports, statements and hand written drafts by Schlesinger. Major legislation included in the collection is the Taft- Hartley amendments regarding whether jobbers and contractors should be treated as separate employers or as a unitary employer in disputes, and the Landrum-Griffin Bill amendments regarding the garment industry and secondary boycotts.
One major component of the collection that is of particular interest is the comprehensive look at racketeering in labor unions. There are numerous clippings and correspondence regarding the inquiry into racketeering in unions, particularly as it concerned the ILGWU. The McClellan Committee was charged with investigating labor-management racketeering. There is testimony before the McClellan Committee, including Dubinsky's deposition and affidavit regarding Johnny Dio (John Dioguardi). Dubinsky denied that Dio was ever in the ILGWU, that he was friendly with him and whether he knew of Dio's mob ties. Newspaper articles and clippings alleged Dubinsky's involvement or at least his knowledge of racketeering in the garment industry, as well as his knowledge of the criminal histories of those at one time employed by the ILGWU, including William Lurye. The files regarding racketeering provide broad research from various sources.
Another key component of the collection involves the racial discrimination charges brought against the ILGWU and the subsequent Powell Committee investigations led by Adam Powell of the House Committee on Education and Labor. Charges were filed against the union by Herbert Hill, labor secretary of the NAACP, alleging racial discrimination against African American and Puerto Rican members of the union. The NAACP called for a vigorous investigation of what they regarded as a pattern of discriminatory racial practices, especially as it concerned minorities in leadership positions within the union. The collection contains testimony, including Hill's, before the special Congressional Subcommittee of the House Committee on Education and Labor. Also available is correspondence, articles, a large number of clippings, notes, statements, reports, and signed testimony as it relates to the investigation.
The remainder of the collection contains articles regarding Dubinsky's resignation as well as the transcript of the public hearing of the "Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Investigating the Garment Industry," including Dubinsky's testimony, as well as a later hearing that took place before the Committee on Education and Labor.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780 OH: ILGWU. Oral History 5780/110 OHT: ILGWU. Oral histories 5780 AV: ILGWU. Audio-Visual (AV) 6036/003: YIVO Project. Interviews in the Irving Howe Collection conducted by Bernard Rosenberg.
Clothing workers -- Labor unions.; Schlesinger, Emil.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union -- Archives.
5767592
- Restrictive labor legislation, Taft Senate Committee, 1937-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Taft-Hartley, jobber-contractor relationship, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Drafts re labor legislation, Taft Senate Committee (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Racketeering inquiry [folder 1 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Racketeering inquiry [folder 2 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- AFL-CIO re racketeering, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- McClellan Committee investigation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Racketeering, correspondence, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Pending legislation, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Taft-Hartley, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- New labor reform legislation, Landrum-Griffin, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- WNBC-TV, Herbert Hill statement, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Powell Committee investigation, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Powell Committee investigation, corresondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Scope and Contents
  Also includes newspaper clippings
- Powell Committee investigation, publicity [folder 1 of 2], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Powell Committee investigation, publicity [folder 2 of 2], 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- O'Hara bill, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Herbert Hill, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- ILGWU corrections to stenographic record, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Corrections to hearings on August 24, 1962
- Rebuttal witnesses, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  For hearings on August 24, 1962
- Miscellaneous, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Herbert Pokodner affidavit, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Powell Committee investigation notes (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Documents turned over to the Powell committee (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Local 60, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Local 600 (Puerto Rico), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Local 155, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Frenetic 7th Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Dubinsky resignation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous, 1934-1953 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Codes, constitutions, by-laws, etc., 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Printed material, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Printed material, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Congressional Ad Hoc Investigating Committee, Herbert Zelenco, Chairman, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Testimony of Schwartz, Local 60; Falikman, Local 10; Zimmerman; other government witnesses; August 24, 1962; Volume 1.
- Congressional Ad Hoc Investigating Committee, Herbert Zelenco, Chairman, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Testimony of David Dubinsky; August 24, 1962; Volume 2.
- Congressional Ad Hoc Investigating Committee, Herbert Zelenco, Chairman, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Testiony of David Dubinsky (accompanied by Emil Schlesinger, Morris Glushien, Max Zimny, Hannah Haskel, Lazare Teper, James Lipsig); September 21, 1962; copy 1.
- Congressional Ad Hoc Investigating Committee, Herbert Zelenco, Chairman, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Testiony of David Dubinsky (accompanied by Emil Schlesinger, Morris Glushien, Max Zimny, Hannah Haskel, Lazare Teper, James Lipsig); September 21, 1962; includes corrections, copy 2.